Chapter 60. the line with reference to the whailing scene shortly to be described as well as for
the better understanding of all similar scenes elsewhere presented. I have here
to speak of the magical sometimes horrible whale line. The line originally
used in the fishery was of the best hemp slightly vapored with tar not
impregnated with it as in the case of ordinary ropes. For while tar as
ordinarily used makes the hemp more pliable to the rope maker, and also
renders the rope itself more convenient to the sailor for common ship use. Yet,
not only would the ordinary quantity too much stiffen the whale line for the
close coiling to which it must be subjected, but as most seammen are
beginning to learn, tar in general by no means adds to the rope's durability or
strength, however much it may give it compactness and gloss.
Of late years, the manila rope has in the American fishery almost entirely
superseded hemp as a material for whale lines. For though not so durable as
hemp, it is stronger and far more soft and elastic. And I will add, since there
is an aesthetics in all things, is much more handsome and becoming to the boat
than hemp. Hemp is a dusky dark fellow, a sort of Indian, but Manila is as a
goldenhaired sarcashian to behold.
The whale line is only 2/3 of an inch in thickness. At first sight, you would not
think it's so strong as it really is. By experiment, it's 1 and 50 y will each
suspend a weight of 120 lb, so that the whole rope will bear a strain nearly
equal to 3 tons. In length, the common sperm whale line measures something over
200 fathoms. Towards the stern of the boat, it is spirally coiled away in the
tub. Not like the worm pipe of a still, though, but so as to form one round
cheese-shaped mass of densely bedded sheav or layers of concentric
spiralizations without any hollow but the heart or minute vertical tube formed
at the axis of the cheese.
As the least tangle or kink in the coiling would in running out infallibly
take somebody's arm, leg, or entire body off, the utmost precaution is used in
stowing the line in its tub. Some harpooners will consume almost an entire
morning in this business, carrying the line high aloft, and then reeving it
downward through a block towards the tub, so as in the act of coiling to free
it from all possible wrinkles and twists.
In the English boats, two tubs are used instead of one. The same line being
continuously coiled in both tubs. There is some advantage in this because these
twin tubs being so small, they fit more readily into the boat and did not strain
it so much. Whereas the American tub, nearly 3 f feet in diameter and of
proportionate depth, makes a rather bulky freight for a craft whose planks
are but 1/2 in in thickness, for the bottom of the whaleboat is like critical
ice, which will bear up under a considerable distributed weight, but not
very much of a concentrated one. When the painted canvas cover is clapped on
the American line tub, the boat looks as if it were pulling off with a predigious
great wedding cake to present to the whales.
Both ends of the line are exposed, the lower end terminating in an eyelice or
loop coming up from the bottom against the side of the tub and hanging over its
edge completely disengaged from everything. This arrangement of the
lower end is necessary on two accounts.
First, in order to facilitate the fastening to it of an additional line
from a neighboring boat, in case the stricken whale should sound so deep as
to threaten to carry off the entire line originally attached to the harpoon. In
these instances, the whale, of course, is shifted like a mug of ale, as it
were, from one boat to the other, though the first boat always hovers at hand to
assist its consort.
Second, this arrangement is indispensable for common safety's sake.
For were the lower end of the line in any way attached to the boat, and were
the whale then to run the line out to the end almost in a single smoking
minute, as he sometimes does, he would not stop there, for the doomed boat
would infallibly be dragged down after him into the profoundity of the sea, and
in that case no town crier would ever find her again. Before
lowering the boat for the chase, the upper end of the line is taken aft from
the tub and passing round the logger head there is again carried forward the
entire length of the boat, resting crosswise upon the loom or handle of
every man's ore, so that it jogs against his wrist in rowing, and also passing
between the men as they alternately sit at the opposite gunnels to the leaded
shocks or grooves in the extreme pointed prow of the boat, where a wooden pin or
skewer the size of a common quill prevents it from slipping out. From the
chocks it hangs in a slight fon over the boughs and is then passed inside the
boat again, and some 10 or 20 fathoms called box line being coiled upon the
box in the boughs, it continues its way to the gunnel, still a little further
aft, and is then attached to the short warp, the rope which is immediately
connected with the harpoon. But previous to that connection, the short warp goes
through sunundry mystifications too tedious to detail.
Thus the whale line folds the whole boat in its complicated coils, twisting and
writhing around it in almost every direction. All the oresmen are involved
in its perilous contortions, so that to the timid eye of the landsmen they seem
as Indian jugglers, with the deadliest snakes sportively festoning their limbs.
Nor can any son of mortal woman for the first time seat himself amid those hemp
and intricacies, and while straining his utmost at the ore, beth think him that
at any unknown instant the harpoon may be darted, and all these horrible
contortions be put into play like ringed lightnings. He cannot be thus
circumstanced without a shudder that makes the very marrow in his bones to
quiver in him like a shaken jelly. Yet habit, strange thing. What cannot habit
accomplish? Gayer sies, more merry mirth, better jokes, and brighter
repares, you never heard over your mahogany, than you will hear over the
halfinch white cedar of the whaleboat, when thus hung in hangman's nooes. And
like the six burgers of Calala before King Edward, these six men composing the
crew pull into the jaws of death with a halter around every neck, as you may say.
Perhaps a very little thought will now enable you to account for those repeated
wailing disasters, some few of which are casually chronicled, of this man or that
man being taken out of the boat by the line and lost. For when the line is
darting out, to be seated then in the boat is like being seated in the midst
of the manifold whizzings of a steam engine in full play, when every flying
beam and shaft and wheel is grazing you.
It is worse, for you cannot sit motionless in the heart of these perils,
because the boat is rocking like a cradle, and you are pitched one way in
the other, without the slightest warning, and only by a certain self-adjusting buoyancy and
simultaneousness of bition and action, can you escape being made a mazeppa, and
run away with where the allseeing son himself could never pierce you out
again as the profound calm which only apparently precedes and prophesies of
the storm is perhaps more awful than the storm itself. For indeed the calm is but
the wrapper and envelope of the storm and contains it in itself as the
seemingly harmless rifle holds the fatal powder and the ball and the explosion.
So the graceful repose of the line as it silently serpentines about the oresman
before being brought into actual play.
This is a thing which carries more of true terror than any other aspect of
this dangerous affair. But why say more?
All men live enveloped in whale lines.
All are born with halters around their necks. But it is only when caught in the
swift, sudden turn of death that mortals realize the silent, subtle, everpresent
perils of life. And if you be a philosopher, though seated in a
whaleboat, you would not at heart feel one wit more of terror than those seated
before your evening fire with a poker and not a harpoon by your side.